I think we should have some like introduction and music like the CBS Evening News or something.
Drum roll.
Yeah, exactly.
Okay, should we call this meeting to order?
Okay, we'll call this meeting to order.
Please stand for the Pledge of Allegiance.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the republic for which it stands, one nation, under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
A nice soggy night, right?
Happy Flag Day, everybody.
Flags are out.
That's announcement number one.
Kevin and I just did that.
Next item is to approve the agenda, and there's, I would like to add under, instead of city attorney's report, since he won't be here, I'll add Wildwood Park discussion.
since the parade is coming up, and we need to get that taken care of.
Can I put a couple things more on my agenda?
I was going to update the community on Comcast, I mean on CenturyLink, sorry, and just update what happened at the planned exchange and the garage sale.
Not a problem.
I move the amended agenda.
Is there a second?
Second.
All those in favor?
Aye.
Opposed?
That carries.
Mike, you get to figure out who seconded that.
I think everybody did.
Announcements, we've got the Across the Lake Swim, July 2nd.
Gene Rooley is here.
He's gonna be the boat person with his wife, being safety conscious and all that.
7 a.m., Birch Beach.
Second item is the 4th of July Parade, which is 9.30, starting at Polly Shank's Old Place, 5 Birchwood Avenue.
Anybody who wants to volunteer, still looking for a little bit of help on that, can contact me.
If they don't contact me, I will be contacting somebody.
So watch out for phone calls from me.
Next item.
Any other announcements?
Good to go.
Next item is the city consent agenda.
Is there a motion to approve that?
So moved.
Is there a second?
Second.
All those in favor?
Aye.
That carries.
Next item is the city engineer and Steve Thatcher is here from Thatcher Engineering.
Oh, Mike?
Did I miss something already?
Rulie would like to.
Oh, sorry about that.
See, I'm always ready to rip a roll through this.
Okay, Gene, public forum, which is a another way of saying the roads committee has commandeered it for us here.
Gene Rooley, 262 Wildwood Avenue and chair of the roads.
I think on that cross the lake swim on the birch easement, let's put a flag up or something so that the swimmers have something that's rather than a tree or something, you know.
It's hard to see from the peninsula, so.
Let's run up something, someone's bed sheet or something.
Randy?
I've heard that too.
I don't know, just someone in town who's got a flag pole.
The flag is no use, but you need a flag pole to get it up in the air, I think.
That's the key.
Well, I tell you what, we can talk about it.
I have put up something as big as four by eight.
You can't see it.
I think Randy just mentioned it.
Would you put up something, Randy?
I don't have any flag poles.
Bed sheet.
We'll find something.
We'll work on it.
Good idea.
It's in the minutes now.
It'll happen.
All right.
We had, I think, an active month with the roads and streets.
The things that we had to confront us, we worked on.
And weeds were mowed, and mud is still where it's supposed to be, but we're on it.
And issues that came up.
were reported to Mike or wherever we had to do it.
And I know that the signs didn't get up.
The person that is doing that didn't move it to the top of his list.
And so we'll deal with that.
But I bet you anything we'll live for another month or a few days, at least, before they get up.
And we've discussed it.
We're working on that.
On our committee of walkways and paths in the village,
We met this last week.
We discussed a lot of different ideas.
We didn't set our next date because we had a couple of assignments that people are on.
One was to get MnDOT to come and see if they have ideas on what would make a street that's busy a walkway.
I think we're
Cedar and Hall, maybe we're devoting too much time just on those two streets of focus for that committee.
There's gonna be traffic there, and the street's only so wide, and so we're looking for alternatives is what we're doing, and we'll see how it comes out.
It's gonna take a while, and they're willing to work, and we'll just go from there.
I don't think we have any time frame, which we expect an answer.
But we do have a time frame for the stop signs.
And you and I talked today.
And I think we need to go to plan B, which is we've got two fellows who do work in the community.
They have tools.
And I think we could enlist one or both.
Maybe it's a two-person job.
But I think it shouldn't be hard to put up half a dozen stop signs or whatever we're doing.
I think we need to do that because I just don't think the other fellow has the time or the, I don't know, doesn't have the time right now.
Can I speak to that?
Yeah.
Okay, so there's several things that have to happen.
First is we need to have a tree service person that can clear trees and brush along the side of the road.
We also need to contact, make marks on where they all go, contact, go for state one call, get all the product here, stay within budget, and then install them.
So it's not just, you know, get a shovel and go out and put some posts in the ground and hope that, you know, it all works out.
So the process being done, everything's ordered, I think everything's actually here now.
Is everything here?
I believe so, now we're waiting for tree service, and we're waiting for a bid from that still, which has been three weeks ongoing.
We're also waiting for Gulf State to come out and mark once we have the spots all designated.
So there's a lot of pretty substantial process.
But by all means, we can have anybody do it.
So there's no rocket science involved in that at all.
You know, I noticed that you folks had made sure the vegetation was cut.
I think we can go one step further and again go through with our handyman to actually clear the
There's limbs and whatnot that you can't see the pedestrian signs, you can't see the speed signs, and everything is just like, I was gone for three weeks, and all of a sudden, boom, I come back, and a forest has grown up in three weeks.
So I think we need to get Jim and Greg,
out there, and that'll solve the problem that you're saying we need to, and you know, I don't think we need a bid for that, it's just an hourly, we don't need to be bogged down with an evaluation of just get out there, get it done, it shouldn't be complicated, it's all in the right of way.
I think the people in the village that work their yard all the way to the street should give some consideration, too, if there's vegetation that they want to have trimmed, that they do it themselves so that it doesn't get wiped out or something.
The big thing is that it isn't hanging over the street or obstructing or what have you, so that it looks halfway decent, too.
I think that's part of it.
Aesthetically, it should be evaluated.
Yeah, and I think the section of Hall Avenue, it's much more wild, if you will, than the section on Cedar.
There's a difference in, you know, just happens to be a natural divide.
People down in Hall, it's more natural.
So, and that's where the trees have really taken off.
I think Cedar less so, but I think we've got an obligation to make sure that signage is available right now.
with the speeds and the stop signs.
I think it shouldn't be hard to do.
It shouldn't be complicated.
Unless you folks are thinking we're trampling on somebody's expectations about how much should be left alone in their own yard.
Well, if it's a bigger tree where Steve or one of the foresters are involved, again, it's a schedule that you deal with.
It seems like they get done sooner or later.
Sometimes it's later.
Well, Steve went and did, you know, he did the whole canopy about 18 months ago with the expectation that that was going to last more than just 18 months.
So, these are things that are just growing out like the buckthorn and the honeysuckle and these are things that are just sort of creeping to the open space to get more sun.
Box Elder, a lot of Box Elders are just gone wild.
So I have a feeling, I mean maybe we could, maybe you and I want to walk the street and say boom, boom, boom, and if there's anything that looks suspiciously nice.
we should warn Greg and Jim, but otherwise it's basically just maintenance.
We don't have that walk path developed yet.
How can we walk the streets?
I understand.
Oh, come on now.
But I think it's a safety issue.
Again, just as we clip the weeds down, we want to clip the trees down, because they're boxing people closer to the road than they want to be when they walk.
We'll take a look at it.
I think we can do that.
But I think it's a Jim and Greg kind of thing.
Does that make sense?
I hear I am, you know, talking too much.
They cut down full-size trees then?
No, no, this is just a... Because the full-size trees have to go down before they can come back and brush.
It needs to be brushed back because we have stuff that, so if you, we pay them to go out and cut down small stuff.
Right, right.
Right on the edge of the tree.
Three weeks later, it's growing back over the street again.
So there's large stuff, that's why I contacted Steve, and he's our tree guy here, I think.
And then, Ken also has this big crazy mower thing, which will go through and do that once the big trees are out of the way, but you can't do one without the other, and so it's kind of a bottleneck.
And the signs, I don't see a problem with the signs being done by the end of the month, but that being said, I don't know.
We're in good hands.
I think it'll get done.
Anything else?
I do like the fact of if you see anything that looks nice on any of the properties, including the one up here on the corner of East County Line and Cedar, that we contact the homeowner, and if they don't wanna do it, then we'll take care of it, so.
I don't know if, you know, I spoke to the owner there and he said he would do it himself and then he didn't and I hesitate to, I gave him the option.
You want me to do it or you want to do it?
He chose to do it himself and I'm a little reluctant to go cut it down.
And I don't think it's on his property, I think it's on the county.
And maybe they should move those bushes all back if they want to keep them.
Lilacs are pretty easy to move.
Easy meaning they'll probably survive if they move them.
I think that's probably something you want to just leave to have Mike do.
So it becomes a city action instead of a gene really action that causes you, you can't win.
But you can help.
Get us started in the right direction.
That part's been done.
Just got the ball rolling.
It's all good.
Good.
Thank you.
Okay.
Stay dry.
Okay, Steve.
Sure.
Steve Thatcher.
We're talking about lift stations, lift station monitoring.
Since last meeting, Mike Anderson and I met with Tim Hilsham and showed him the lift stations and discussed his monitoring of the lift stations.
And Tim and two others are interested in providing monitoring services to the city.
So with Mike and your water operator's help, then we've got five people who could share the 24-7 response time of, say, 15 minutes for lift station number two.
I'm talking with Tim Hilsham and two others.
All of them, all those three have sewer operators licenses.
They are currently employed by the city of Lionel Lakes.
They have approval from their supervisor at Lionel Lakes to provide this service to the city.
as soon as the city decided to go on further with this and evaluate this, the current plan, the way I understand it, that we left it with Tim was that Berkshire Village would contract with him, the city,
I mean it's his company actually, not just him personally, his company.
And then the other two people would be part of his company.
So it would be a contract between the city of Birchwood Village and Tim's company.
So they wouldn't be an employee.
of the City of Birchwood Village.
None of it is set in stone, everything's negotiable, but it wouldn't be through the City of Lionel Lakes.
You wouldn't be contracting with, the City of Birchwood Village wouldn't be contracting with the City of Lionel Lakes.
The other way we left it with Tim was that,
that it would be very logical for the city to prepare a list of their responsibilities, what we want them to do for monitoring, and then send or meet with him to discuss it and modify it with their help.
And then Tim would take that and put it in a draft agreement between his company and the city for the city and the city attorney and everybody to review.
before you actually went and did anything on it.
That's how far we progressed on the issue of who's going to monitor the lift stations and how it can be done.
Then we talk about the switch to the other subject of the SCADA system.
What we've talked about is determining precisely who owns that skating equipment.
And I'm not sure who it's going to work on.
I think maybe you were going to check into that some more.
I haven't heard results of that research yet.
You know, Steve, a couple of things.
If you could set the table of how we got to this point,
You were involved in some analysis, and we've been struggling with what to do with the lift stations.
And I think you've uncovered some information that maybe everybody isn't aware of.
So give us background on how we got to this point.
Sure.
A little background is that over the past
I wanna say a couple years, you've had real high costs in relation to, one, the services of just monitoring the lift stations, and number two, you've had real high costs in the repair work of any kind of service on the lift station, including replacing the impellers, including the contractor, electrical guy, kindly coming out and
doing whatever they can to get the SCADA system to work.
It just boggles my mind as to why they spent so much time and energy trying to get it to work when there are other ways to do it.
So the whole objective of the exercise is to get a situation where you're minimizing cost and still maintain the same response time
that you have now, that's the overall goal as I see it, unless you guys see something different on the goals.
Right, and we still haven't, as far as it seems to me, the SCADA is still sort of like
It's online, but then there's an issue, and the issue is... It drops out.
What would you call it?
A communication failure.
It's a communication alarm.
Right.
And so if you have a communication alarm, then somebody has to go out and determine what's wrong with it.
And a lot of fail comms or comm fails.
and they don't seem to go away.
Right.
And so one way to avoid that or to minimize those is to switch to a cellular system, meaning instead of the signals being radio, it's phone lines.
Not hardwired, but regular cell phones.
The signals could come either
Well, even if you stayed with the SCADA system and sent the signal to City Hall, you'd have the information here at City Hall rather than over at White Bear Lake Township.
The same thing could happen with the cellular system.
But with the cellular system, the information would come right to your cell phone.
And as many people as you wanted could be on that, the warning system.
So those people could see, oh, there's an alarm.
And if that one person who's on duty for some reason can't respond in 15 minutes for lift station three or whatever time period you set up for the lift stations, then he could quickly call somebody else and they could respond.
But it's on your cell phone and not at an office someplace, either White Bear Lake or the office here.
There's less things to break down if you have a cellular system.
And I haven't gotten into details or listed all the advantages and disadvantages of each one because we weren't exactly clear on who owned the existing SCADA system that you've got there.
I know you paid for it.
I know you paid a lot of money for it.
But it wasn't clear to me in the documents I've reviewed, you know, which are, you know, these documents here.
And there are probably some other documents that maybe you have.
who actually owns the equipment that you paid for.
Well, if we paid for it, wouldn't we own it?
Well, I mean, there's a couple of parts to the SCADA system, the PLCs that got put into the lift stations.
So we would probably own those.
Probably.
It then becomes an issue of who owns the radios.
On that, that could be disputed because there's the radio at basically White Bear Township, the master radio, and then there's the
Satellite radios that are go at each one of the lift stations kind of thing.
So You know and so and so we have that I know that my own company we have a mixture of Cellphone we have a diverse portfolio because everything breaks no matter what technology you use.
They all have different failure modes.
So I
We'll use a com, I mean, and the trend in the industry is to move to a mesh radio, which Randy and I have been talking about, you know, long term would be a good thing for us to do.
Short term, not feasible.
Randy and I have kind of already discussed that a little bit, so.
So, cell phones are good technology.
We looked at it a few years ago in terms of a cloud service.
So, there's a couple of companies out there who will,
plug your cell phones into it and they'll monitor it and they'll send you an alarm on your iPhone or on your Android, depending on what you want.
and you can acknowledge the alarm from your iPad or whatever.
So they're pretty cost effective because you don't have to buy the computer, you don't have to buy the $50,000 worth of software and all the services.
So it's just pretty much a canned application which is very attractive for small municipalities.
But there's a couple of different people who offer that, right Steve?
Oh yeah.
Yeah, so it's a good choice.
Would you have to have both running, both for a little bit at the same time just to make sure when, like the cell wasn't going to work?
I mean, like just you can't turn one off and get the other one going or?
We would have to kind of walk around with, you know, see who has the more, I mean, in some areas Verizon is the better offering, in some geographical areas AT&T is the better offering.
No, I meant will you have to have the SCADA and the cell phone run at the same time just to like,
make sure there's not that?
There would probably be a period of a few days of overlap.
Okay, that's fine.
And then there's ways of where we could send a signal to both.
Okay.
Yeah, so it's also if you, if for some reason the people that are operating the system for you now have some claim on ownership of whatever equipment that's there, if they have a claim on that, we should know that before we figure out what really is the cost going to be for us to switch.
and then we can analyze the cost of, is SCADA better for your situation, or is the cell phone better for your situation at the current time with what we know right now?
So it seemed like the next step in the critical path of analyzing what's the best thing to do for minimizing costs in the sewer is to figure out who owns what on the SCADA system.
Okay.
You're talking about radio telemetry versus cellulophone telemetry, right?
Right.
Yeah.
A question for you, Randy, because you're right next to the lift station.
I was down in that area today and tried to do a text.
And it seemed to me you were in a black hole for cell phone use.
Is that a factor?
Because I couldn't get texts out until I got up over the hill.
Personally, yes, there are.
That's why we've got a landline at our house.
We can't get it.
But I'm going to say this, though.
I was able to get some local Wi-Fi at the boulevard from a neighbor's house.
Oh, yeah.
Different issue.
We did check the cellular phone signals at each one of the lift stations, and we were able to get a good signal at each one of the three lift stations.
AT&T or Verizon.
Verizon.
Okay, just a, just a, you know, anecdotally a question.
Are you with Verizon?
Yeah.
Oh, okay.
Yeah, and they're good.
I thought.
Until today.
What?
Is your phone?
No.
okay this commercial paid by so um Steve one other question about this whole scenario is because you know we've got the elephant in the living room which was the the limited size of our holding tank
because that's a liability that just seems to be there and not go away.
So how does this factor into your analysis?
Because we don't have, I don't know if we have 15 minutes from what you.
Well, you may not have 15 minutes.
We're figuring the 15 minutes based on the two years worth of daily flow data in this,
Every day, someone reads the running time meter at the lift station, and we know how much the pumps pump.
So it's a running time meter analysis to get the data.
So that has some inaccuracies in it, just to begin with.
We took that two years' data, and we come up with an average daily flow for that time period, then using engineering numbers.
to factor up to where we can say the peak day is X number of gallons per minute and the peak hour is X number of gallons per minute.
And then based on the size of the storage tank that is there, because we measured it, we could say, well, yeah, before it gets into the pipe itself, it's clearly 15 minutes.
And then we don't know the amount of storage that's in the pipe.
or the manholes that are upstream from before it actually floods back into a house.
We just don't know that information.
So yeah, there's a very short period of time.
And no wiper had to be there within a half an hour.
Oh, it's less than that.
It's less than that.
In fact, you know, what he's saying is they had a half hour call out.
We saw 15, 20 minutes.
Well, when we did the test, and you know, that was like eight minutes.
When you did the test, you turned off the pump, and then it backed up to the point where it was now going into the pipe.
Relatively speaking, I know the pipe has volume, but relatively speaking, not much.
Eight minutes seemed to be sort of like you're starting to push the envelope in terms of how much space you've got left.
Right, and then the manholes upstream too, they're four foot diameter, so you've got some storage in those manholes, but again, not a lot of storage.
So there's a very short period of time
The critical point is that on lift station 2, if you have an alarm on lift station 2, it could be many different things.
It could be that one pump is out for whatever reason.
But if one pump's out, you don't have to get there in 15 minutes because the other pump's still working.
And you could have that information on the cell phone saying, oh, yeah, the other pump's working.
So then you wouldn't have to respond in 15 minutes.
The time when you would really have to respond fast is if all the power is out, or if both pumps have stopped for some reason, or if there is a high-level alarm.
meaning, you know, both pumps are stopped or something's wrong, the flow is not going anywhere, it's backing up.
Then really the only thing a person can do is show up, look at it, and then oftentimes it's first call is to a vacuum truck company to come out and start sucking up the waste water from the wet well.
and hauling it away until one of the pumps is working again.
So it's those critical points is when you've got a high-level alarm.
It's most critical.
That's where we go on, right?
Right.
It's going down at one time.
Well, I don't think you've had many power failures here.
And if you had power failures, they've been short.
And now you're putting in a backup emergency generator.
which is operated by gas.
So if you've got a power failure, you've still got gas to run the emergency generator to run the pumps.
But you can still have a failure of something on the emergency generator, or the automatic transfer switch, too.
So you can still have all those problems.
Anything's possible, but your limits go way down.
Your chances go way down.
The risk of having a backup is less and less.
It's a smaller and smaller amount.
I guess what I was asking is, knowing that we have limited capacity, how does that filter into the timeframe or timeline of what you recommend?
In terms of any change or no change?
The decision I see on whether or not you want to increase the capacity, the emergency storage capacity of lift station number two is independent of what we're doing on this SCADA system and the monitoring.
That seems to be an independent decision to me.
That can be separate.
You can do nothing on that and rely on people to respond quickly.
And I don't think anybody's done this analysis, but how much money do you save if you have a larger storage capacity?
Meaning you spend a lot of money to have that larger storage capacity.
How much money do you save every month or year because you've got that larger storage capacity?
Meaning are you going to save monitoring time for someone to go look at that?
You know, we're typically going to, I think we're going to have the people come and look at the lift stations maybe once a week, but that's about it.
There is some benefit to have someone come, you know, once a week, and we can talk about that further in greater detail, but having someone come once a week is really helpful.
Even if you've got the emergency storage capacity?
That's large.
I'm not sure if that's answering your question.
No, it did.
The other thing that got us to this point was, I think, the fact that we were going through impellers every year or two, and that they should be lasting 10 years.
So that was, I think, sort of what precipitated this whole conversation.
And how does that issue get addressed in this equation?
Right.
I'm analyzing the records that you've got.
that Mike gave me, and I don't have an answer yet on the frequency that you've actually had on the impellers.
I do know that you've had, at lift station number two, rags in the wet well and garbage bags in the wet well that they've sucked out recently.
I know these are things that are really uncommon in a sanitary sewer system, but they do happen.
The impeller data that I saw and talked to the people about and saw pictures of the impellers that they took out and replaced showed a lot of wear and tear on the impellers.
Lift station number one, the impellers there showed signs of cavitation meaning
the air gets on the impellers themselves, and then when the pressure changes in the fluid, it cavitates and pushes and collapses the airspace and damages the impeller.
That lift station number one also has had some situation where they've had air locks, meaning it wasn't sucking like it should be.
And so they did put in impellers, new ones in there, and hopefully you won't have so many of those callouts.
When were they put in?
It was either the latter part of last year or the first part of this year.
Okay.
So it's very recent.
But the impellers show a lot of wear.
The, you know, when we went with White Bear Township, which was January, I think, of last year, at that time we were told there was garbage bags in the wet well, and the impellers were worn to the nubbins.
I know that, and I know we had them replaced.
So now we're told again, the impellers are worn, so you've got a year and a half that's transpired, and they've worn out.
So there's your time frame.
I know there's another shorter period as well, just previous to that with the replacement.
So that still needs to be addressed.
Yeah, the data that I've seen on the bills, I've seen where they replaced the impellers on both pumps on lift station number one and one of the impellers on lift station number three.
And they put in a whole new pump on lift station number two, which means brand new impellers and everything.
Yeah.
And I haven't gotten all the way back on the records, but I don't know that there is records that go real far back.
Well, we were just wondering if we had to do something different in order to make these things last longer, because I thought we were told it was a 10-year period in which we would look at replacement.
Yeah, the pellets should last about 7 to 10 years.
They really should.
So, while you're seeing it occur sooner than that, I still don't have an answer yet for you.
But I haven't gone through all the records yet.
The newer toilets got larger throats on them.
And they'll take down almost anything compared to an old toilet that would plug up really easy.
So if there's any kids or anything out there, if they put something in the toilet, they hit that lever, it's gone.
It's going to end up in our system.
I believe that's where a lot of our problems are.
It'd be interesting if you could talk to us, maybe some other cities, or if everyone, it's not just Birchwood who's ran through Impeller, it's maybe other cities are too.
Maybe next month you can tell us, I guess, or let us know.
Most of these things have a three inch throat on them now, so I don't care.
If your keys fall in there and it gets flushed, they're gone.
Well, and I think, you know, just to bring this together, I think what happened is we had the impeller issue.
It was costing us a lot of time and repairs.
Steve got involved.
He looked at the big picture and said, well, you've got some other issues going on.
What can I do to help?
And now he's come back with this analysis.
You're just giving us an update and so we'll expect something when?
Right.
I think the next step would be to make sure that we know who owns these equipment and then based on that, I'll get prices for and analyze what's the best thing to do with monitoring the list stations and SCADA system so it actually does work.
And impellers then too?
Yes.
Okay.
Right.
It's just sort of a
a report, an analysis of where we are and what we can do to do better.
Yep.
So far today, it's just an update.
Okay.
Sounds great.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Okay.
See you next time.
Sounds good.
Thank you very much.
Have a great fourth.
Yep.
Thank you.
Okay.
Home Energy Squad presentation.
Randy, this is something you talked about?
Yes.
Hi, Randy.
Hi.
I spoke on the phone last month.
And do I just signal to you for the next?
Okay.
Well, thank you for inviting me to come in and speak to you tonight.
My name is Terry Chaney with Neighborhood Energy Connection, which is a 30-year-old nonprofit based in St.
Paul.
We partner with
Excel Energy to improve energy efficiency in Minnesota households.
The mission is pretty simple.
We improve people's lives by making energy conservation easy.
And the ways that we do that are through our home energy squad visits, energy audits, rebates,
helping to complete energy projects and sometimes financing for the work.
And why it's important, one of the big reasons is cost.
We spend a lot here in Minnesota.
Another reason is a more efficient home is more comfortable and less harmful to the environment.
And this is a breakdown of the typical Minnesota homeowner's energy usage.
And it also reflects energy costs.
So our programs are designed to address these main areas.
Next.
And one way to think of improving energy efficiency is a series of steps.
And NEC can help you achieve your projects step by step wherever you are along this metaphorical staircase.
But a lot of people, like Randy, are introduced to our organization with a home energy squad visit.
Oh, I'm sorry, next.
Look like Ghostbusters.
They look like Ghostbusters there.
Kind of has a Reservoir Dogs kind of.
And a lot of people may recognize the iconic transit, which is what we bring to your house when we do the visit.
And the energy-saving items that we install in your home are designed to pay for themselves in one year.
And since most people have busy lives, the Home Energy Squad will save you time by installing these items for you in one visit at an affordable price.
able to deliver the program at an affordable price because of the partnership with Excel.
And the average visit is usually about an hour, sometimes as long as an hour and a half.
And during that time, we can install the items you see here, weather stripping on your door, low-flow shower heads, and faucet aerators.
programmable thermostats, water heater blankets, and we'll replace your incandescent bulbs with CFLs.
Also, the visit includes a walkthrough assessment where we check your furnace, the water heater, your attic insulation, and then can make recommendations based on what we see.
And I'll just go through a few of the items in a little bit more detail.
A lot of what we do is replacing incandescent light bulbs, which are inefficient.
We put in CFL bulbs, which last longer.
They also use 25% less energy.
And for comparison, a 13-watt CFL bulb puts out about as much light as a 60-watt incandescent bulb.
You guys have not moved over to LEDs yet then?
We do offer those a la carte right now, but we're... Just with all the CFL problems and mercury and disposal and stuff like that.
Yes, definitely.
We do contract with Excel, but yeah, in the future, that seems to be the direction that we're headed.
Perfect.
Thank you.
We also can install...
low flow shower heads and faucet aerators.
And in addition to saving water, they also save gas.
Most faucet aerators in our homes already use about two to two and a half gallons per minute.
The ones that we install use one to one and a half gallons per minute.
And if you don't already have a programmable thermostat, we can put one of those and set it up for you as well.
It's one of the easiest ways that you can save money in your home.
The EPA estimates that for every one degree you set back in an eight-hour period is equivalent to saving 1% on your energy bill.
And if you have a lot of these items installed already, you can also schedule home energy audits.
We use diagnostic tools like the blower door test and the infrared imaging.
And that can reveal air leaks in your home.
We can also provide a profile of your home's overall energy performance.
And the energy audit can be scheduled as a standalone visit.
It can also be combined with home energy squad visits.
And just a quick word on the phrase energy efficiency that I've used multiple times.
I just wanted to highlight the distinction between our work doing energy efficiency and renewable energy because they can and often are used interchangeably.
And there are different approaches to reducing energy, but can also be complementary.
Thus, for those that might be considering a solar project, it's often economical to focus on energy efficiency first, and that way, when you do your solar project, more of your home can be powered by the sun.
As I mentioned, the programs we offer are affordable because of the partnership with Xcel Energy.
The cost of a typical visit is, for the home energy squad, is $70.
However, we can often offer those for half off if we're doing visits in the same geographical area.
And we believe it would be possible in Birchwood Village over the next year to do 50 visits in your community.
Other cities that we have worked with have helped us promote and do outreach at local events, on social media, in newsletters, and we hope to work with you as well in ways that
you think would be appropriate here.
Anyone watching can also contact me directly by phone or email.
If you want to learn more.
Michael have your phone number and stuff here too at City Hall.
To learn more.
And with that, I will say thank you.
And if there's time, if you have any questions, I'd be happy to.
I just wanted them to come here because they came to my house.
They came to my house.
And literally, when they left, I had a bag of light bulbs for $35.
They weather-stripped the door, replaced some shower heads.
And it's like, how can you lose?
They've been to my house before too.
When it was a consortium neighborhood energy consortium st.
Paul neighborhood energy consortium way back when yeah So my child's doing the energy audit in the picture Yeah, yeah, you know my wife used to work there forever, so yeah
Yeah, and Excel will send out occasional emails and might put a little flyer in your mailing.
But otherwise, it's kind of on us to do our own outreach.
Works out well when we partner with cities to help reach more people because like Randy was saying it really is You know a valuable service so Yeah, we would like to work with you to would you work with our City Hall here is that not a not a family I guess this well, we're more residential but
Okay, they just work with residential.
What what is the average cost of an energy audit where they put the for the blower door or the infrared scan?
Yeah, the the The blower door that's kind of the standard audit.
That's $60 and the infrared is a hundred total or both total
Are there bulbs that we can replace all these?
You counted them?
We have over 70 fluorescent bulbs in the building.
But these are energy efficient.
Well, no.
The new LEDs, actually, they make the LED equivalent of fluorescents.
And they are considerably cheaper to run than the fluorescents.
There are rebate programs to help you make the conversion.
Why don't you use the mic here?
Yeah, this is Danielle, by the way.
She is a co-worker of mine.
I think Excel has rebate programs for, I mean, they work with Home Depot.
I shouldn't plug them, but for the LED discounts, if you want to do that, I know that they have the discounts if you need to replace a furnace.
They have discounts if you go to a geothermal.
They have discounts if you do a foam insulation, like a hot foam in your ceiling, which is very energy efficient.
That can really tremendously reduce your cooling costs.
I work for Excel Energy, so I have to, you know, I'm just plugging the company, that's all.
Okay.
They do good work.
Sounds good.
So if you can work with Mike and Mike can coordinate something on the website, that'd be great.
Newsletter, an extra newsletter maybe.
Okay.
I did leave some packets back here that has more info about the other programs.
We offer my cards in there, so let me know if you have questions.
I would say if you're a citizen watching this, take advantage of it.
You'll see it's well, well worth your money.
Randy, if you want to put something in the newsletter, then just get that to me by August.
Yeah, and if there's any way that I can help with that, just let me know.
Perfect.
But if there's a coordinated visit, then we could do something that could lower the cost for people even more, it sounds like.
The combined visit?
Yeah.
Yeah, the combined visit.
The price on that is, well, you schedule that with Excel.
And if you do the combined visit, then the home energy squad portion ends up being $20, and the audit portion is $60.
So it's a total of $80.
You pay $20 at the visit for the home energy squad, and then Excel bills you for the audit portion on your utility bill.
Good, all right.
Okay, all right, thanks for coming.
Thanks a lot for coming, appreciate it.
Okay, next item is the MS4, Stormwater Pollution Prevention Program Review.
At this point, I'll open it up for public hearing, which has been noticed in the White Bear Press.
I move we close the public hearing.
Okay is there a second?
Second.
All right all those in favor?
Aye.
Opposed?
This is something that we're obligated to do following up just giving public notice of what we've done in the past year.
Mike you want to just give us a heads up on what's going on with that?
with the report that's due?
Well just you know the fact of what this is and what it entails.
Oh yes thank you mayor and council.
The MS4 stormwater pollution prevention program is just a report that's due to the state on an annual basis.
The city's plan for how they handle stormwater and stormwater drainage throughout the city and the, I believe the measure of the catch basins as well.
We're required to have a public hearing at a meeting and the report is due at the end of June.
This is the same form we've used for how many times in a row?
The permit is every five years and we started in 2013 so it is the same technically until we have to reapply in 2018.
And it's a licensing program, so I think they charge us $400 a year for the benefit of giving them the report that it's pretty much the same every year.
But we do monitor our catch basins, and in fact, they were monitored last month, and half of them came back as not needing any attention.
So there are just a couple that do need to be cleaned out.
So I think our street sweeping program and maybe our salting program has caused our amount of sediment going into the lake to be less than previous years.
I know, talking to Mike, I think we kind of fell off of the wagon for this cleaning out the catch basins and things like that, but I think you're figuring out a schedule now, aren't you, Mike?
Yep, I've been working with mark on that in the last couple weeks I've received three bids from separate companies on cleaning out the catch basins in the past We've done one in the fall and one in the spring and considering none of the basins need immediate attention I would like to get that back onto like an October April schedule If that's okay with the council, it's just an inspect and clean if needed.
It's not like it's a every time they go out and suck it so
Well, we monitor our own catch basins.
So we do that spring and fall.
Rather than bid that out, it doesn't take but 45 minutes.
But on the basis of that, then there's an obligation to, if they're full, to have them cleaned out.
And as I said, there are five that need to be cleaned out now.
And I don't know, I mean, just so you have a ballpark, Infratech does it for $220 a basin.
And I couldn't find anyone cheaper than that.
In the past so what we've done in the past we just call them up say no granted there might be somebody who comes in cheaper and that'd be fine, but it's That's what we that's been our ballpark in the past.
So we missed our spring monitoring.
No, we got done That was the list that I sent you was just measured in April, but there's a but we're in mayday mode to clean them out though.
I
Well, once the report was just done, I think, three weeks ago.
And on that basis, then... No.
On that basis, when they are full, because we monitor them twice a year, we say, okay, these need to be cleaned out now.
when they hit a certain level.
So there's no reason for spring and fall contracting then it sounds like.
We just monitor them ourselves and then.
I didn't word that correctly.
We monitor twice a year and then clean as necessary.
You can go ahead and have a company probably do it, but I don't think, like I say, when I've
In the past, I had gone and, oh, you do stormwater clean up.
Great.
How much is it?
And prices can be astronomical.
And Infratech has been able to accommodate us.
And we just say, these are the addresses.
These are the ones.
And it gets done.
They're pretty good about it.
$220 a catch basin was the last cost.
Mary, do you need a motion to approve this filing, this form?
What do we need here?
think no I think that's just administrative it's a public hearing we're obligated to do that and this is just an update to the council okay okay the next item is
The next item is Sherry bus, and you know knowing that we have a meeting tomorrow I'd ask that we just continue that item to for discussion until tomorrow so make sense sure I will not be here, but okay, and then On that basis I would also recommend we not adjourn, but we just recess until tomorrow so we carry over that business at that time
We'll get to that at the end of the meeting.
Second reading then of the structural height code language.
Mike, do you want to tee that up?
Yeah, I just have mike give a little brief intro before we do that.
All right.
Thanks mayor and council, um over the last six months or so we've The council and planning commission have been trying to come up with some Language for our 202 30205 045 structure height code language to kind of make it better understanding On how to calculate the average structure height per building We've come up with a few
different paragraphs with different wording and isn't quite clear.
And then you'll see option two that is provided in the packet, makes it, simplifies the language to make it easier to calculate the overall structure height.
Okay at this time I'll open the public hearing to discuss the proposed code options.
Is there any interest in that?
Okay need a motion to close the public hearing.
So moved.
Is there a second?
All those in favor?
Aye.
That carries.
So I think it's safe to say we've had a full discussion on this topic.
And there's two choices that I asked Mike to put on the second one, which is our previous code.
And if you go back and look at our previous code, it's not much different than what is being in option two with the changes
It basically takes out the roof issue of how do you measure a roof and what's the roof line and what are the variables when you have multiple roofs.
And it basically gets us back to where we started from with the DNR.
And then incorporating a grade plane.
And so those are the issues the city council needs to wrangle with.
And I would recommend in either case exhibit C, which is included in option one.
with the illustration for grade elevation that exhibit C actually would be exhibit A referred to in the second code, in the second option.
It should have been put in there again.
So you get the intention of how you calculate these numbers with the simplicity that we seem to eventually get to with
when we've done it with tree ordinances and other issues.
And I'm not sure what the council, how the council wants to proceed, but those are the two options.
Is there any other comments?
And once we pick an option, we go to the DNR for approval then?
I think option number two has already been approved by the DNR, so we basically say, we've cleaned up our code, so it's clear to everybody.
Here's what it is.
We'd want to pick an option and then run it back past the DNR again, and then they would say yes, not that.
Mike, have you had any contact with the DNR?
Mayor and Council, I have tried in the last month numerous times to get a hold of the DNR with no response.
I don't have Alan here, we don't have Alan here tonight, but I would think we could confer with him, knowing if we went with option two, that we basically already had DNR's blessing and we don't need that again in order to accomplish that.
I think what we're doing is...
clearing up the issues so that we don't have this misunderstanding and misinterpretation.
I think on 232 Wildwood, we had about three different interpretations of how the code applies.
And despite the fact that we've tried to clear everything up, it actually became more muddled.
I think we need to get back to something more simple.
And the DNR signed off on this before.
I guess I would recommend we talk to Alan before we say what we have to do with the DNR, but we might be there already.
I don't know, I think we should still send them a copy.
Oh, yeah.
By your silence, UVIX.
Are you going to move forward on option two?
I can second that.
Okay, any other discussion?
I think that you've set out, I think, some great reasons for doing it.
DNR has kind of signed off on this.
It's simplifying the code.
I mean, this thing, it's going to come up again because it is such a confusing darn, you know, and people keep pushing up against that height and it's, somebody's going to find a loophole in what we did.
So it's like, but we're going to give it our best shot.
I guess that's what I want to say, so.
Any other discussion?
Okay all those in.
Sorry we will talk with Alan and then have an actual approval by the DNR.
I mean that was kind of a big deal so I think we should have an actual DNR says yes there's some kind of stamp there from the DNR saying yes yes yes yes then we're it's in.
Well, I had spoken with Mike before the meeting.
I think we can table it till tomorrow.
Mike can come up with a summary resolution.
We can adopt the summary resolution and have that then approved at that time that conforms with this language.
And then Alan can enlighten us.
Knowing that this is basically what we've done before, Alan can enlighten us.
What do we do next?
it might be helpful Mike if you could take our exist the 2000 code if you have access to that and just show the few changes that were made from the 2000 code and I think substantively there isn't much change it's just in an explanation of what these items mean just your three things strike out and underline everything yep yep okay
So I think we can deal with that all tomorrow.
I know Alan will get back to us by tomorrow.
Whether the dean does, I think he'll enlighten us.
What do we do next?
OK?
There's a motion.
Yeah, there's a motion to approve it and then give final approval tomorrow.
That's right.
Sound good?
Yes, good.
All those in favor?
Aye.
Any opposed?
That carries.
All those relieved?
Aye.
Yeah.
Okay.
Randy, you're up.
Some updates.
I'm pursuing talking about LEDs, replacing all the streetlights in Birchwood with LEDs, which will really significantly save money.
We've talked about this before.
I'm actually kind of trading phone calls with a person from Xcel Energy.
I mean the question comes up who owns the lights and thinking it's one of those we'll figure these things out that and we'll also when we talk to the people from Excel is it gonna be worth it to do it or not to to replace for us to replace them or not so well the light burns out we replace with an LED
That's what they're doing now.
They said they've actually placed two lights in Birchwood already with LEDs, so I don't know which ones they are.
That's probably the least expensive way of going about it.
If they come in and do it all, then it's going to hit us really hard.
Actually, Accel says they're on a two-year schedule to replace all the street lights in basically this part of the world with LEDs.
So that's on a two-year schedule to do it.
So it's already happening.
That's what I heard from the guys.
That's what I was told too.
So pretty much everything they're replacing with LEDs as they're burning out.
That's right.
They're just replacing the whole kit and caboodle.
It's just cheaper for the company to put in more energy efficient bulbs and reduce energy usage because then they don't have to build another power plant.
For a little while.
Well, they haven't in a long time.
Yeah, they're real trying hard to meet their PUC requirements.
You know, Randy, Chris had looked into this issue before he left, so at least a year ago.
And the communication he had with Excel was, yes, it's coming online.
Yes, it's coming within the next two years.
Yes, we can do it for you.
And yes, it'll reduce your savings by about 8%.
Yeah, 7%, as I would heard.
So I'm off by a little bit.
Anyway, but we know, I mean, from an analysis, we know that the cost of electricity is significantly.
It's like 15% of the total cost.
So other communities have, you know, the payback period is, I think you said it, like five years or something.
So if we get ahead of the curve, we can, I think what we'd be saying is we are entering into being our own utility.
That's right.
Our own, yeah.
And I don't, you know, that might be the way to go because we know we're going to get a net benefit.
Absolutely.
If we wait too long, then we've got Excel that says, well, we've already changed out half of them.
What are you going to do now?
And how are you going to do it?
So time might be of the essence.
I am.
yes I'm working on it no no I'm just saying and so the question is you had you had said who owns the lights are you talking about the ones that are out there now are you talking about the ones if they get installed ones that are out there right now it's like there's all such ancient history is what's part of what would be the cost if we were to do it though because then when I was told like I think we need to get some firmer estimates but the estimates I've heard $300 to $500
mean but that is what part of that estimate is there is a basically Excel doesn't have to put a monitor how much energy is being used in every single light which would make it prohibitive which would make what make a prohibitive so for us for us yes right and yet you would think the Public Utility Commission would help us out on that so no no no Public Utility Commission has not been helpful whatsoever
The, you know, there's about, you have to take off the ornamental lights, because they're a different animal, and we've got, you know, we've got about, what, 30 of them or something, 25?
Those are the ones up in New, kind of New Bridgewood up there.
Oak Ridge, no, the ornamentals, they're half as high and like three times as expensive.
They're on a pole, they're up by you.
no others yeah there's some up in Kevin's area and there's Oak Ridge couple we installed yeah no yeah that's what happened in the subdivisions time but we have let's just say we have about a hundred lights and I think the price that we were paying was was 15 and I think Bill said the price would go up 15% so we're looking like 18 grand so you're looking at each light being what about 180 bucks a year
So if you say the cost of purchasing it is $300 to $500, and we know the cost of electricity is minimal, it won't take long to pay for them.
At Central College, they replaced all their lights.
It's a different situation.
They said their bill's going to go from $18,000 a year to $1,800 a year.
So it's like, but we'll have to, you know, that's something they'll be able to tell.
I think Excel, hopefully they're going to be up front and tell me what's going on.
They said we can actually replace, I talked to actually a contractor from Peoples Electric, and we drove through town, we can replace all those lights on Oak Ridge with LEDs too.
So that's doable.
So yeah, I mean if you're talking 180 bucks a light, there's huge incentive.
mean the average something the average those LEDs will last 55,000 hours right and so it's like that's I mean that's the average so we're gonna last longer so I'll ask shorter so let me I'm excited about this I think it's gonna be a great improvement for virtue and save us a lot of money
I think the answer is a political answer more than it's a physical answer.
What can we do?
So the bottom line is, who's going to own them?
Is Excel going to own them, or are we going to own them?
We would own them.
We'll own them.
If we own them, then they have to put a meter at each one.
We don't know.
That's the question.
But I've heard that they figure out how much it's going to cost, and they just send you a bill.
We put a meter on one, then they say, well, this is what it's going to cost for everything.
I mean, that's something I'll figure out with them.
And then they'd be kind of on those lights, which you were mentioning that we would enable them for a future mesh network.
Yeah, that's right.
So down the road, when they put these in, there's actually, if you hate to say it, at the top, a little plug-in where you can actually attach and perhaps Wi-Fi when it becomes feasible.
It's like, OK.
These lights that I've talked to, it's like, they're really cool.
I mean, the lights they're putting in,
you can really control how much light goes up and down, almost like a motion detector type of a situation too.
So, it'll be exciting to see what kind of technology we'll be able to get for BirdToy.
So, that's cool.
Very cool.
Okay.
Other communities have done this, so it's not like we're reinventing the wheel.
know so well it kind of as part of this interestingly came so the we don't really have a right-of-way ordinance here in Birchwood and I was it possible married to have our Planning Commission take a look at this right-of-way ordinance I mean the city the League of Cities has like a 40 a
some page document.
I mean, the right-of-way is like, well, so why do we need a right-of-way ordinance in Birchwood, for example?
CenturyLink wants to come in.
They could decide, we're going to put in poles and just put in poles right next to all the other poles in town.
Or we're going to dig something underground and not have to worry about ruining people's yards and things like that.
So I think if the Planning Commission just takes a look at it, they've got some short versions or long versions.
If we could ask Alan first.
Yes, yeah.
I mean because I don't know why somebody could come in here and start putting things in our easements without permission and I don't know.
Because they're big and they can do it.
I don't know.
But perhaps.
That's happened in the past.
Pardon?
It's never happened in the past.
Exactly.
I mean, you know, Quest comes in and says, we want to be a franchise, so we need permission.
So everybody seems to ask permission.
But Alan's got to have a good idea.
He's doing the work.
He does it with Maplewood.
And then if Alan gets his two cents, put our planning commission involved.
So I'll leave this.
Is Alan coming tomorrow?
We'll put it on for tomorrow.
Kind of segues into all these things together.
CenturyLink is getting closer.
That's all I can say.
There's been some, about half the towns that they've been negotiating with have gotten agreements.
The other half haven't.
We're in the other half that hasn't right now.
For?
Getting an agreement, getting a contract with CenturyLink to come into Berkshire.
I'm just Joe Citizen right now, so if you're
being solicited by CenturyLink for internet.
Is that different?
Yes, because they're talking about TV.
All right.
That's what they're talking about, cable TV.
So they're going to be able to give you more bundles, because they do internet, and they have more competition, lower prices.
That's right.
They do more competition.
That's a theory.
Better service, but we'll have to see.
So got to make sure they jump through all the right hoops.
So that's coming.
As soon as that comes through the Cable Commission, we'll feed it back to the city, City of Berkshire.
Is that their field system, FIIOS?
I don't know.
OK.
plant sale we had 30 some people here exchanging hundreds of plants that was fun again we'll see us in the fall garage sale there is like about 15 18 garage people selling stuff and giving stuff away so we'll keep on doing it okay I'm done Mike
update on the deer report yes thank you mayor and council last month you asked me just to gather a little bit more information regarding John London eyes
research on the deer population here in Birchwood.
I provided you with a memo in the packet with the information that I'll summarize here.
But I did contact the Department of Agriculture, and you'll see the fee to get roughly 25 deer out of town to bring it down to the seven to nine deer that Birchwood should have is gonna cost in the ballpark of about $8,000.
includes eight scouting visits, three hours each, five control visits, and some hours for some meetings.
And then you'll see the 35 deer option a little bit more.
Some of the requirements to do that, you know, it requires another meeting with some public input from the residents.
The DNR permit requires that the residents are notified in some manner.
So wherever the hunting area would be, like a mailing, kind of like a variance mailing every house within 200 feet.
And then if the city did decide that they wanted to move forward with an option like this, well, we would have to get the permit through the DNR gentleman named Scott Nolan.
I was also asked to contact the surrounding communities to see what they were doing for their deer population.
I contacted White Bear Lake, Matamitai, Grant, Willerney, and the township of White Bear Lake.
And as of the end of last week, I've only heard back from White Bear Township, who already partners
with Ramsey County with their efforts in their parks.
But I did not hear back from the other surrounding communities.
But the White Bear Township also lets their residents apply for permits to bowhunt in specific areas.
With that I'll yield to any questions or how would you like me to proceed if any?
I think we need to do more work to get the rest of the communities involved.
Whitebird Township and I think I think it'd be nice to
have White Bear Township be inquired about again, because there's no bull hunting on the south side of the lake.
And their parks are on the west side of their township.
So this is a different area that what we do affects them.
And so I think a more full conversation should happen anyway on that issue.
No, yeah, but I did talk to Dale Reed, and he said that the residents in Wiper Township, close to Birchwood, he has not heard any complaints regarding the deer in that part of the neighborhood.
All right, so a conversation, though, with White Bear, with Willerney, with Montomedi, with... Grant is too far afield.
I wouldn't spend your time with that.
But those communities... I think especially Montomedi, because that's the pipe that comes right through Kevin's yard,
So I I think they need to be involved in a discussion and and Cost-sharing because I thought we were told that the price was $200 per deer and now it's gone up to $300 per deer So I think there needs to be some sort of cost sharing because it's it's a regional issue It's not just us and I we can't solve the issue alone So I agree with that I will
get a hold of those communities and have an update for you in July.
Okay, last item then is Wildwood Park.
We've got some issues down there.
They're not getting better.
Mike, do you want to kind of set the table on that?
Yes, Wildwood Park, as you, the mayor and council know, and a lot of the residents know, the building site at 232, the
Builders have been parking in the park, destroyed the grass.
I've been informed that they will re-sod it.
They're supposed to re-sod it by the end of this week, early next week, and have it finished for the 4th of July.
I do have it in writing that the builder has agreed to do that.
but they, even after asking them many times not to park, the way they do, they still continue to do it, and I've had to go down there numerous times to ask them to move their vehicles out of the center of the park, as well as the drainage down there in the drain.
I've had to ask them to clean it out numerous times, and with the large rain we've had the last four days, it's just become an ongoing issue.
So you've given them plenty of warning, so why aren't the police involved now?
We'll just have Jack go over and put a hole in the house, a hole in the construction project or something like that then.
Whatever works, I don't know.
He'll be able to do something.
I will start calling the Sheriff's Department if they continue to park.
Did they get called today?
I did not call them today.
I personally went down there to the site and asked them to move their vehicles.
And they were there again, right?
There was one in the center of the park again today, yes.
Mike, I don't think we can do anything to say we're asking.
This is a poor use of your time.
It's a very poor use of our time and our resources.
This is a park that is a centerpiece of that neighborhood and it's extremely disrespectful that they don't honor that and they don't live here and they don't have the consequences of what they're doing and I don't believe that they'll have it started by the end of the week.
I just don't because there's been no proof that they will follow through with anything you've asked them to, and we're now in a mode of telling them.
And Alan's not here tonight, but we need to have, make sure, I don't think we can red tag the house.
I don't think we can, but if we can, I have no problem with that, but I don't think we can.
But we need Alan on board to give these guys an ultimatum about what they need to do and what they must do and what we will do and what it will cost them and how we'll abate the cost.
Because I don't want to go into something where we pay for it and then we try and scratch to get the money back.
So this is a point of no return.
They have dishonored us in every sense of the word in keeping that neighborhood appropriate.
I was, as I mentioned to you earlier today, I was going by the Piccadilly project in Montemita yesterday, and at the end of the day, they pulled out their gas-powered street cleaner.
handheld one, and they cleaned up the street before they left.
And that's not being done here, and that sediment is now going into our catch basins, and we're paying the money to extract that out of the catch basins at 200 bucks a time, which is, you know, expensive.
The street is like a couple inches deep in mud.
There's no excuse.
There's no excuse for this.
And, you know, we happen to have a meeting tonight, so we can bring this to a head.
Had we not, they would continue to misbehave.
So I think it needs to be made extremely clear to them, and as a matter of fact, to you.
The cops need to be called, because they know these guys have been given notice not to park, and they've been given it in writing, and the cops need to act on that.
They say, we can't do anything until these people know what they can and can't do.
We also need to have some no parking signs up there.
And I know we've talked about that, and it seems to me we've got to get those up immediately as well.
I thought we had them on order.
We have them.
Are they ready to go?
We're pulling the ones out of Ty Schmidt.
Perfect.
Posting everything.
Gone.
That's my two cents.
I don't know how everyone else feels about it, but to me it's gone on too long.
Any other opinions?
Ellen's going to be here tomorrow?
Pardon?
Is Ellen going to be here tomorrow?
I don't know.
I don't know for sure, but I'll ask him tomorrow.
Might be a conservation meeting.
It's the third Wednesday of the month.
I think we should have a pretty robust conversation.
I know someone, Mary or Mike, just talked to Alan saying we need something ready to go now for these guys.
I mean, now, to me, it's like... Now?
Well, now they've got a mess with the mud.
I mean, it's rained.
It'll have rained over three inches in the last two days, so it's like, I don't know.
But they drive their trucks as if it's pavement out there.
I know, I know.
And they back up and they roll forward.
I walk by it two or three times a day.
Yeah.
I'm surprised there haven't been more complaints.
The level of patience has been exceeded in whatever's reasonable.
We're nice people on Wildwood.
So, right, I think it needs to be done, and it needs to be done now, and Alan needs to tell us exactly what parameters we have, but I think there's an abatement remedy, and I think there's a time period where we have to act.
So, anyone else?
Make sense?
All right.
See you all tomorrow.
So I'm going to suggest that we recess this, and so I need a motion to recess until tomorrow night at what time, Mike?
7 p.m.
tomorrow night.
Make that motion.
Is there a second?
Second.
All those in favor?
Aye.
That carries.
Stand and recess.